But first of all, we'll go through and put the picture
and explain what osteoarthritis is for something.
Thanks for being here, great fun to sit and talk about this disease.
Yes, osteoarthritis
can you say is a result
by an imbalance between build -up processes
And disrupting processes in the trail.
It is not as many people think a pure wear so that one mechanically wears
away the cartilage without it depends on a biochemical change that makes
that the trail is redone and
The tissue is affected.
And why does this trail come in imbalance?
There are a number of different causes and then you usually talk about risk factors
affect pain processes in the body, among other things.
Another common risk factor you talk about, then it is age.
As a rule, osteoarthritis does not affect young children.
But you can see it in young people after a sports injury for example.
But as a rule, it is after the middle age that the illness increases.
And age can partly stand for processes related to aging itself,
that genes are expressed so that the tissue becomes weaker
The more we age, but also age stands for time.
Time you have gone
Around and been overweight or time that has passed since you injured their joint.
And damage is too
A very strong risk factors especially for the knee joint.
When fighting can harm structures such as meniscus or cruciate ligament and that is then
associated with a greatly increased risk.
Another risk factor that I would like to mention that is then
Osteoarthritis is more common in women and it is especially after transitional age.
And why it is so is not entirely clear,
But I think it has to do with hormonal adjustments.
But it is probably not quite that simple anyway, because you haven't had any special
promising results or seen any clear finds here
by replacing estrogen and that it would lead to less osteoarthritis.
So there is also more research to be done to understand
Why women are hit just after the transition age.
Another thing that I think is important to mention it concerns osteoarthritis then also
is that often you have
not only osteoarthritis but it is common to be affected as well
So it is very common.
The problem of course lies in
risk factors so these diseases
are common risk factors.
But also when you get osteoarthritis
So you become less active because you have pain in joints.
And when one is less active,
So there is a higher risk that you may become overweight and also get other diseases.
For example, diabetes or heart disease.
What we see is that people who have more than just osteoarthritis,
They report more pain.
So they have a worse
Lead disease and this can also affect.
You become even less active and it becomes more difficult to move.
Increases the risk of type two diabetes, so we talk about age diabetes.
But there is also some evidence that there are other relationships as well,
There also increases the risk.
It can go in both directions there.
And it is research that is going on.
To try to clarify a little more about the mechanisms.
But I just want to underline
what Andrea says it is important to
Just that one does not end up in it
Here downward spiral then.
That you become sedentary,
One can get overweight and which increases the risk of
Cardiovascular disease and type two diabetes and more.
So it is
the basic step in treating disease.
To try to review their lifestyle and become a little more mobile.
Yes, then we will come to the next question.
Just mobility.
Those who go and get osteoarthritis
Often get pecific movements and exercises to do.
How to think about increasing one's mobility and activity?
The most important thing to understand is that even if one is in pain, it is not
Bad to move.
You do not need to rest when you have pain in the joints.
It is very common for you to think that one can
Tighten on and damage the joints because you are in pain.
It is interesting indeed,
We see that it is much worse for the trail
to just rest.
It is important to stay active and
You can think a little what happens when you do not exercise a muscle.
A muscle becomes weaker and the same happens in the joint.
If one does not use the trail,
So it becomes weaker.
So it is very important to meet a physiotherapist who can
give some suggestions on how to become more active even if it
hurts the trail.
What one can say is that even if one has
and cannot exercise or move in several days,
You understand that it is not so easy when you are in pain.
But if the pain goes back for 24 hours then one can the day after
go shopping or walking or exercising.
And many have asked if there is a specific workout.
We don't know that.
The research cannot point to a
Exercise that is best for osteoarthritis.
The most important thing is to do something that is lasting and fun.
So you don't sit at home all the time even if you are in pain.
Without maybe go out, meet other people so it gets
A more healthy lifestyle, not just be sitting all day.
It is a relatively simple message, you can say anyway.
Whatever you get started.
It is more important than doing specific exercises.
Yes absolutely.
It is interesting too
our ancestors, they moved very much
For thousands of years ahead, we were hunters and collectors.
And these are the genes we inherited so that the body is
After all, built to move and stay started.
And there are also theories that it is our changed lifestyle that
has been done for the last 40-50 years with more sedentary and diet that contributes
Also to why osteoarthritis increases as much in scope as it does.
But if we look further back in time so
If you moved so much and had a completely different diet than we have today.
Sure, one has seen that also prehistoric people
got osteoarthritis actually, so that this is this that one of
Our oldest known diseases.
You have even seen it on finds from dinosaurs.
On skeletal parts, on finds that indicate that it is like at osteoarthritis.
One has also seen on prehistoric people who lived 40 \ h000 years ago
in caves in France that there were osteoarthritis on
In that case on the spine of an individual.
So it's an old disease.
But we also know that incidence is increasing sharply in modern communities,
And it is probably very lifestyle -related and that we become sedentary,
Our body mass is increasing and we don't get that exercise
We need and then the tissue does not get the quality.
Who can help a little and get over this.
For one is very scared when it hurts,
And we understand that it is hard.
But, as I said, you can guide on what is reasonable.
Can you cure osteoarthritis?
There is no cure in the biological sense.
When dealing with the final stage in osteoarthritis, when you have tried all other possibilities,
This is when you insert a prosthesis.
But there is no cure in the biological sense.
But there is needed
more research and there is a number of different in the world
actors to find
Especially drugs that can affect the disease process itself.
For the treatment we have today available,
it is really basically symptom relief
And you would like to find something that can slow down this one
the process or get the trail in balance.
I talked before about constructing forces and degrading processes.
To get them in balance again and to
prolonged this process or even stop it.
Or at best to reverse, that's the ultimate.
And one already has today
In research contexts there are a number of candidates that are examined
What is it?
Pain is complex.
Pain is not just due to structural changes
Without it, it is a very psychosocial process as well.
A pain that is important and that is why
In the case of symptom -relieving treatments, it is
Like not a treatment that works on everyone but one can try out
And find something that works for this particular person.
And it can be different ways what the treatment looks like.
But the first step that is important, this is exactly what Andrea is talking about.
Getting information about the disease and you can get this in an osteoarthritis school.
Get to know what it is and meet others who have
and exchange experiences.
But also to look over their lifestyle and try to get started and be a little more
moving and give the joints the exercise they want to feel good.
And these curative drugs not today,
You have before that in 10-15 years, maybe the first will come?
Yes, I think so, because there are already promising candidates today.
But it is important to point out that these drugs are quite specific
Which may work for a particular type of osteoarthritis or for a particular joint.
So there is no one
Miracle cure that helps for everything.
Without one can say that osteoarthritis
It's almost like a collective name for when the trail fails, which it can do
For many, many different reasons.
Such as
A joint may fail for having a previous joint injury
Where you may have lost meniscus tissue and there then overloaded.
But biomechanics play a big role.
But there is also other osteoarthritis that are more hereditary.
It comes in several joints and in fingers and hips and there may be others
Mechanisms that are important.
Without even within the same stage there may be different kinds of osteoarthritis.
So today, what you do is relieve?
It's exercise and so maybe cortisone?
Yes, the basic treatment is then
osteoarthritis school by reviewing one's lifestyle
look over one's weight can be reduced weight if you are overweight or can
At least make sure you don't increase anymore, this is a good condition.
And it helps many.
But we should be honest with that many have a lot
trouble even after being in osteoarthritis school.
Osteoarthritis school is an arrangement, a training program.
Yes exactly.
There are many who of course have trouble after that too, and then you can
Talk about additional treatment and there are a number of different ones.
I should not say cortisone in the first place,
It is a rather controversial treatment,
But I know it is common.
But it is very directed just at the inflammation,
And some kind of osteoarthritis
can cause severe inflammation.
But otherwise not
Inflammation The main cause of pain.
And partly so gives cortisone syringe
a fairly short -term effect, and there are also reports that
It may have undesirable consequences for the joint
If you give it on repeated occasions.
So that one might save it
the treatment to when you are in the latter stage.
As one begins to approach and
maybe a candidate for being prosthesized and one has not so
much more to take and you see that it is a powerful inflammation
involved, then I think you can try cortisone and evaluate how it works.
But otherwise there are, there is,
It may help, but that is also what one as a patient in consultation
With his doctor comes up, to try out and evaluate.
Does that help me?
Try putting it out.
Will the pain come back?
And so on.
One should also be honest
and say that the symptom -relieving treatments we have,
the greatest effect of them
This is what you really call the sugar pill effect.
Placebo explains the biggest improvement no matter what treatment we give
Partly that and partly the natural course.
Because most often it is like that
That you start taking treatment when you are in a bad phase of the disease.
Artrus pain often fluctuate over time and people tend
To seek care when you are a bad phase and that is when you get treatment.
So no matter what you have given pre -treatment, it is often a little improved.
So that there are actually very nice research data on it,
one has seen over many of those
symptom -relieving treatments, one has done
of the improvement that occurs after the treatments is explained by
Placebo and natural fluctuations.
So only 25 \ h% is attributed to an actual
Effective effect and the treatment itself as it was directed.
And this applies to all these treatments in principle.
It also speaks about what need we have today
To find better, more effective treatments.
Because we want to find treatments that are more effective than a sugar pill.
Do not underestimate the effect of the sugar pill,
But you want to find something better.
Is it related this psychological about pain that you were in?
Yes, that's a big effect.
Pain sits inside the brain too,
so many of the treatments that work
Is a lot of a body and mind type of exercise.
One can mention yoga, tns, acupuncture - to believe that it works
And the context around it makes you feel better and that is an important part.
And it's totally okay, but what to think about maybe as a patient
is what is the cost to me?
Do you have anything else to add?
No, the best thing is not to eat too much
And try to eat good food, not too sweet.
So one should think as usual,
As you do not always do, but you should always try.
One can well also take the look back to our ancestors
They ate a much healthier diet than we do today.
Today we eat
very very fast sugars
and it
affects the risk not least for type two diabetes.
There are connections to stress and low -grade inflammation,
As a cause of osteoarthritis?
Yes, absolutely that is a cause for many diseases.
And we see that osteoarthritis is linked to multi -illness.
Stress and low -grade inflammation are common risk factors.
So there is another risk factor in some sense?
Absolutely, and it is linked to diet as well.
What one eats can affect,
How to move as well as the weight.
Everything affects very clearly
the inflammation found in the body.
I agree that the particular pain experience
can be greatly affected by mental stress.
But I don't think there's a lot of evidence
which indicates that mental stress accelerates the process and degradation in itself,
But on the other hand, the experience and the pain.
is clearly dependent on
Our well -being and if you have a life in balance.
Good to find out.
This is also why training can help because we know that training affects our mood.
So even if it's the same pain,
So you experience it in a better way and it is also very important.
Exercise often makes that
allows one to form body -by -endorphins
Especially at high cardiovascular workouts
Where you get a high pulse and such.
Many may recognize themselves in that
You feel quite satisfied afterwards.
It may be hard but afterwards you feel the endorphins
It is a great and difficult question.
It often goes in forests,
The pain and
There are certainly things
Who triggers this but there the knowledge is lacking today.
But one can say that one thing that can trigger
Is an overload simply.
You may have a joint that has not really managed what you have entered into.
One may have run a marathon on asphalt, because
Take something extreme, and then it can trigger.
But otherwise, depending on the trail, there are also many patients
as reports that it has to do with climate, that it hot
or cold and so that it can also affect
the pain or process.
That you become more swollen in your joints in some type of weather.
But this is a pretty unexplored field, but also quite difficult
to study such forests, because it requires one to have
Many patients who report their forests.
What exactly did then?
But it is a very interesting field to actually look at.
The recommendation one can give
It is well that you are observant yourself as a patient.
Can one see any relationships yourself, and try to adapt
Or avoid the torque or what you have done now.
Maybe it's good to think that when it gets a little worse,
that it might have been a little worse last week
But that does not mean it will be even worse.
But as I said it goes in the forest that
Is part of the usual process, so nothing unusual.
There are also those who have
More chronic pain, which sits evenly.
Especially at a later stage of the disease.
But does it go in the forest but still down?
Are there some who have a forest and so can it be better?
Yes, that one has osteoarthritis does not need to
mean that it will only be worse and worse.
There are many patients who have lighter symptoms and it has the life out,
Provide favorable results even on structural changes.
Some questions about connections here.
Virus, viral infection and someone asks about Crohns.
Gastric disease Crohns.
Yes, there are two separate questions there.
Me, of course, there is no known virus that triggers osteoarthritis
However, there are a number of other related diseases
which may be associated with infections in the body.
A classic example is that one has a bacterial infection like salmonella
or campylobacter, unless you have cooked the chicken properly then it can trigger
Start a joint reaction where you get severe swelling and pain.
But it's not osteoarthritis without it
is another more inflammatory acute rheumatic disease.
So there are connections between infections and joint pain.
But as far as we know today there are no viruses as you know
is associated with osteoarthritis.
And when it comes to
Crohn's disease, which is an inflammatory bowel disease,
There is a very strong connection with joint pain.
And the first thing you and the doctor should think about, it's probably this one
second type of disease that often comes with
This inflammatory bowel disease.
And it is an autoimmune reaction that
trigger the immune system and then it becomes an inflammation of the joint.
There are many different types of joint pain.
Yes exactly.
Osteoarthritis is the clearly dominant, but then has
We a group of diseases that involve very severe inflammation.
Type example is what is called Arts Rheumatism or
Rheumatoid arthritis in medical language.
There are a number of other diseases that are
closely related to that group.
Palliative physiotherapy?
As we have said so we talk about
the treatment as a pyramid, one starts with exercise
And if it doesn't work,
can you add any type of drug, and at the end comes
the operation, you have tried all the treatments and there is no
other alternative then you have to talk to the doctor
and decide if it is possible to get
A prosthesis for example.
It is these supplementary treatments, and there are a variety of strategies.
It also depends on which joint is affected and so on.
But orthoses, ie rails if one has
pain in a finger, there may also be some for knees
and so on
that can be aids that can make the troubles become smaller and which can
help one in everyday life.
Largely.
But that's what Andrea says,
The important thing is to give
To be physically active a chance, to get started a little.
For it may, if nothing else, delay and the symptoms
becomes smaller.
And maybe the prosthesis will come later in life.
You also do not want to put in a prosthesis too early.
For there are also many young people who have osteoarthritis early
in life.
There are 30-year-olds and
Then you want to try to delay
the operation litigran, because
a denture does not last forever, although it is very long
survival for the prosthesis and it maintains good quality, so it always
More trouble to replace a prosthesis.
We live for a very long time today.
It is a discussion between treating physician
or the orthopedic and patient.
And it is important to say also
That the pain does not disappear completely for everyone who receives prosthesis.
Some are still in pain afterwards
Therefore, it is important to try other treatments.
To be sure
on that they do not work and then
If you get a prosthesis, even if you can have a little pain after.
But then you know that you have tried everything.
And it is also not risk -free with prosthesis.
It is around 20 \ h% that still have symptoms after surgery.
You then look at co -morbidity,
Do you then have severe obesity, you have diabetes type two and you have heart problems
Then the desire to put in a prosthesis becomes a little less with us doctors.
Because one knows that
Then the risk increases significantly for problems
And complications and infections and that there will be bad results.
So that's why it is important regardless
that one looks over over one's lifestyle
and their body mass, trying to train the muscles and be prepared
as possible for an operation.
One gets better results
If you have a strengthened up
Your muscles a little even before surgery.
Someone wonders here about alternatives to surgery,
For example, cultivate cartilage and you do this in some sense.
Yes there are stem cells after all
Almost a fashion word for many years in many diseases,
There is research going on with stem cells
In principle, inject them into the trail.
To grow the cartilage.
With the Lotten's help you decide who to get placebo
and who is to receive active treatment
and so on.
So one has seen
In some other less high -quality studies that it might give
Some results on cartilage growth or some form of tissue are formed.
But results on that it should be better than one
did any other treatment,
It's not today.
There is much left to prove from that type of treatment.
But one cannot fully write it but we are still waiting for better
studies in order to see
What it entails.
But then it is also a treatment method that is directed
more to a specific type of osteoarthritis where one might have a
Local cartilage defect that you want to repair and so on.
The hard thing is to use it in a joint that is very long time
And totally lacks cartilage.
Focus today is mainly on a younger patient who may have had a
joint injury where you have damaged the cartilage, where it has died on a
Some surface and so you want it to grow back.
There was someone who wrote that I got my shoulders
And it works perfectly.
It is great with a patient who thinks it works perfectly.
But that said, I am not convinced that it has that effect depends on
a therapeutic effect of the stem cells themselves, but it may be that it is
Just being taken care of, get a syringe and paid money for it.
This makes you expect to feel better.
But as I said today in science, there is no evidence and
This is why it is not one
recommended treatment from the National Board of Health and Welfare for missing
Simply is evidence that it is effective.
There you have not been able to show any effect beyond the sugar pill effect
In the studies that one has reported,
Without there, placebo has provided similar improvement.
Is it also one to say fashion treatment?
You can say.
It is an expensive treatment that is located
A little in fashion.
Do you have to pay private then?
You have to pay that privately.
This is a huge market for people to make money from.
This is a very grateful market.
It is not only these experimental treatments, it applies to all forms of
Because it is a grateful group to make money from.
People who are in pain are desperate and want to find a treatment.
Yes, for supplements there have also been questions.
Is there anything to say about it?
You can not
Completely written off that there is a health food that can help with the pain.
Absolutely not.
But again, there is no evidence,
Good studies that show that they have a better effect than placebo.
But at the same time, if you can get a placebo effect and it is safe,
And it doesn't cost that much, that's good.
And I think it works.
But to be critical too, do you feel better?
One can try to put it out, put in again and then make a balancing if you
I think I feel better about this and the cost picture is okay.
So, take it!
You have to observe yourself, and test yourself.
Yes.
And as I said, there is not a pill that helps for all kinds
Except that you have to try out a little what you think.
Do you want to add something there when it comes to health food?
No what you say is right.
The same goes for exercises and training.
When we don't know
If one has osteoarthritis is then
Greater risk of getting it in several joints?
Yes and no.
One can say that
Do you get osteoarthritis
in a knee joint because you have damaged it
But rehabilitation goes well and so on.
But you have developed osteoarthritis
you keep body weight normal and you are active and
So it is not necessary that the risk increases for other joints.
Then it is no.
so you often get surgery to try to repair the knee
Or the trail, but now is it a little uncertain what is best?
It seems that exercise is as effective as surgery
And there is some surgery that you should not do.
For example, peepholes where you go into the knee,
It can be good when you go in to cook the damage,
But if it has been many years if you got the injury
When you were young, and you have gone without the operation for 10-15 years
Then you should avoid.
Because there can be brokenness in progress, and then you should not operate.
Maybe Martin can explain further?
The important thing I think is not to overload the joint
In the acute stage without letting the damage heal
well as possible and then gradually train your LED again.
Because when you have damaged a joint and become still, you lose muscle strength,
one loses stability and perhaps the injury in itself has caused one to have
Lost stability.
And in this case it was a fracture then
In the cartilage surface and it needs to heal as well as possible and then you get then
gradually increase the load.
We still know that overload is a strong risk factor.
For osteoarthritis.
So biomechanics are important.
But again as I said initially,
that it is
not so that one mechanically wears down the trail, but it becomes a
imbalance between constructing molecular processes
and degrading molecular processes.
And there is biomechanics and the load
An important part of controlling this balance.
And there is after all
in occupations with very high heavy load
So it is also an increased presence of osteoarthritis.
One -sided high load, carrying heavy things
And it is also something you can think of.
Do you have an injury so maybe
You should review, if you are still professional,
what is it for
work task you have.
Talk to his immediate boss and tell us about this.
That I need to find alternative tasks for me
or resolve it in a different way in order to avoid
Just to strain an injured joint unnecessarily incorrectly.
Then we are in on movement and training.
And we already that the best training is the one who gets rid of.
And when it comes to running, is there anything more fellow there?
Because there is one who says I got worse when I quit.
Yes, you have already said that it will be.
Is there anything about how to run for example?
Or any tools?
It is very specific and depends on each person.
My suggestion would be to meet a physiotherapist
And get an evaluation of all the muscles and how to run.
For example, is there a muscle that is weak because one has
had pain and as one might get a specific exercise for
that reinforces the muscles and that can help one run properly.
And it is very important how to plan your training.
Not to run a lot just a day and then get a huge pain.
But maybe make it a little more gradually, try running and see
how much you can and maybe
Run a little more every day and build up their workout.
There are support bands, can it help?
Yes support bands and there are different shoes that can help because we all run in different ways.
Because it stabilizes.
And also applies even if you can't run, if you are older so
is it important to have good shoes, a pair of great jogging shoes
and not go out in anyone
bad sole or high heels.
Really have comfortable shoes that have good cushioning and stability.
It facilitates, and you can also take aids such as orthoses or support.
Here is one who got the advice to go on uneven ground
In the forest for example.
Is it good?
Yes, it can be good if you can and do not have too bad.
It is good for stability and balance because the muscles have to work a little harder
And it's a type of exercise.
You can start by walking in town where everything is flat and light.
And when it gets okay,
So you can try something that is a little more difficult, for example walking in the forest.
But you can say that you have very large osteoarthritis and have
hard to go so may not be that
the ground one should give up first without there maybe it is better to have
Flat soil so that you do not risk falling over or being damaged.
So it depends on what phase
Also, one's illness is.
Many also ask about osteoarthritis of fingers or wrists.
What else can you do than exercise?
A little grip exercises and such?
Here, tools are very important.
There are many tools that can help a person open a can
in ways that load the joints less
so that it gets easier
in everyday life.
Finger arthritis
has been a challenge to treat.
There are not so much alternatives.
One can also imagine
There is local anti -inflammatory gel as one
can try lubricating with for example,
But in some cases it also ends with surgery.
Especially at tumbas arthritis.
Then the operation can help if you have really severe problems.
But it is known to
one has tried some rheumatic drugs in the hope that it
But the results have not been so promising there.
Someone asks, as a matter of drugs,
Is there research on LDN, low-dose naltrexone?
Yes it is
an opio blocker that is really
A medicine used to wean addicts
What I understood.
I quickly looked what was there,
And there is nothing we are researching for ourselves.
But I looked a little quickly in literature what the research says,
There have been some reports there
A certain type of arthropod patient.
But as I said, in the studies have been done so far
have not been so compelling.
Connected to the hands and pain,
If you have severe pain that you cannot tie your hand,
is it just the pain one can fix or exist
Something that can stop this degrading process?
Yes, there comes again this degrading process and it is going on
Intensive research to find drugs that can slow down this process.
We are not there yet
but the fact is that at the last meeting I was on so
that in the long run it should at least lead to minor symptoms.
That's what you hope.
But these are difficult things.
It takes many, many years to do studies to get credible results.
And as I said, research is constantly going on.
If all the cartilage is gone pretty much
In the trail, what result can you get from physiotherapy or exercise?
We have not found a connection between the pictures,
How the knee or trail looks, and results
from training.
So you can't
say before you have tried training, whether it will be good or not.
As we said before, don't worry about the X -rays.
Exactly, we did in a study together with,
it was implemented in the US many years ago, where we took
MRI images of randomly selected people from the population both with and without symptoms.
They were aged 50 to 90, thousands of people.
There we took magnetic camera image on their knee joint
And looked at what was in it.
And there we found broken meniscus, in about half of them.
And the vast majority were
People who had no symptoms at all.
So the risk of man
It may be another joint disease, which you want to exclude.
The second reason
to take mainly
X -ray is also that if you are a candidate
To be operated on with prosthesis so you want to look how
The anatomy looks in the pictures and we see the structural stage.
Then it is important to have a camera, but also to confirm the diagnosis.
But otherwise there is nothing that you as a patient should strive
Asking for, that's not the important thing.
The important thing is how you feel.
And there is a pretty big drive
still from patients, that I want my X -ray
I want to know what it looked like.
But it's wrong, don't worry about it.
It's a bit hopeful.
Although the X -ray image looks a bit "screws"
Or if you happen to have an MRI image where there is a little screw on the cartilage and the meniscus is
A little tabby, there is no great drama about it.
Especially if you have come a little to the age, because we all age.
When I look in the mirror
So I don't look like I was 20 anymore.
I have a gray beard, dropped my hair, I have wrinkles.
It's not that weird,
It is the same with taking a picture on my knee and comparing it
With when I was 20, you get some screws with age.
It does not have to mean that it is illness, but we age.
And the interesting thing is, we have talked about placebo.
There is also something called Nocebo.
That when taking a picture,
And sees that it doesn't look like when you were 20,
Then you get worried,
and begins to feel, the knee is a little different
one thinks very much on the knee or on the trail all the time
And it can also be bad.
Yes, and it can crack and burst the neighbor without having to be anything.
Yes, it is very common.
It is cracking and breaking in joints.
It is normal.
Sure it can crack a little extra if you have ended osteoarthritis
But that it bursts a bit in a joint, it is completely normal.
You don't have to worry about that, there are so many other structures that can slip
And tendons and other things that can give away such sounds.
We'll see, we continue a bit to
And look at the issues that have been received during the broadcast.
We probably won't be able to do with everyone,
But we can see if we can take a few.
First question, is there research on great impact
that it is a high impact on the quality of life in arthropod patients.
There is that.
I remember a study that said it was
in class with a rheumatoid arthritis, another disease that I
mentioned earlier, that it was least at least equivalent
in the influence as that group of patients.
But I think it almost shifted,
Now there is very good treatment for that type of rheumatoid arthritis,
While arthropodic patients still lack such a type of treatment,
So the impact of quality of life is huge.
We know about that.
And much more research is needed.
Now I don't really know which one
Treatment it refers to.
Maybe you know that?
I know there is a study done
On horseback, a Swedish study.
I do not know at all about which preparations and so on.
One has seen the result in
That it gave less heel in the horse among other things.
Stem cells were apparently referring to, in treatment on horses.
Yes, it probably wasn't in this case, but anyway.
But one can say generally that the step from different
And already within man so
There are many different roads that carry osteoarthritis.
And then you take from another animal species then it is not safe
That the mechanisms are the same as in humans.
But it is very exciting to follow if you now take on and want
try different types of treatments
with which you have had success with other animal species, also into humans.
We look forward to this very much, to see if it can produce results.
But the problems are many to make it work.
Regarding cortisone then
You mentioned short -term effect and that it most dampens the inflammation,
But do you see any disadvantage in taking cortisone, for example by osteoarthritis in the shoulder?
In addition to what you have said.
The disadvantage is that there is certain
Evidence for repeated treatments may
Make the cartilage quality worse.
There is, but it is not entirely clear
But there is some evidence because there are risks.
Then you have to weigh
The benefits to the risks.
Is it that you think you get a great relief under someone
week or several weeks
and it increases one's quality of life much
So maybe you are prepared to take that risk.
A slightly increased risk of the structure being affected.
If one has tried other treatments
For the alternative otherwise is to insert a shoulder prosthesis.
And that is a great operation.
Precisely, it is important to man
not thinking about cortisone as a treatment that one takes life out
One can try, maybe it helps at the moment
No, there is no good evidence
because it works
In addition, then the placebo effect.
And what kind of diabetes is it gives risk?
Type two diabetes.
Is cold or heat as relief, preferred?
If any of that now helps?
We know that cold has a pain -relieving effect,
So a cooling light?
Yes, for example.
It does not affect
osteoarthritis or the disease process, but you can get less pain.
You can try both, it can help.
Just.
It is about, that if one has pain
in a joint, to stimulate it with cold
or heat, it makes you get input that exceeds
Maybe this pain impulse so that it suppresses the pain.
Our brain is allowed to handle an input about the cold
This way you can "fool" it.
We all know that if you are injured then you want to
Feel free to keep it and then you give stimuli, that you hold.
Then a little pain impulses are attenuated.
It is a bit the phenomenon you use with heat or cold.
Several wonder if there is a connection between osteoarthritis
And osteoporosis, so weakened skeleton?
Yes, that is an interesting question.
There are some evidence that they like
If you have a lot of osteoporosis then you have less osteoarthritis
And vice versa.
And that just
osteoarthritis is connected by having
The opposite of osteoporosis, thus quite strong skeleton.
It is probably still one
open question, but there is some evidence
Because they are like opposite ends.
Then there is a long gray scale in between,
But I know that many operating surgeons have noted that they
Rarely looks very osteoporosic arthropodic patients, but the opposite.
Often, the skeleton is quite stable built.
And it may have to do with, for example, that many who get
So it is best to think
that if you have huge pain then it is good
To rest a little and wait for the pain to go down.
And then work out again.
But if the trail is very swollen,
so it means there is an inflammation, something going on
in the trail.
As Martin said, it is bad to burden an injury.
So, moving is very good,
But one must learn when it is best to do
And when to rest a little.
So little swollen joints hands often by osteoarthritis, but if
It is much worse today than yesterday
Then it is good to rest a little, wait for it to go down and then work out again.
We have to take and round there.
It might be to
We can answer
In Facebook threads on there are remaining questions.
But thank you so much to you who have looked and thanks to Martin and Andrea!
Thanks so much!